Finding Aid for Angus Campbell Papers, 1949-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Angus Campbell Papers
1949-1980
Campbell, Angus, 1910-
85111 Aa/2
Survey researcher, director of the Institute for Social Research of the University of Michigan. Correspondence; survey files detailing studies of political behavior, racial attitudes, and the quality of life; files relating to his University activities and his involvement with professional organizations; and speeches and publications; and photographs.
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Professor Campbell's office and was the gift of Mrs. Jean Campbell (donor no. 6894 ) in January 1983.
The collection is open for research.
Angus Campbell was born in Leiters, Indiana, on August 10, 1910. He attended public schools in Portland, Oregon, then went on to study psychology at the University of Oregon and Stanford University.
Prior to coming to the University of Michigan Campbell taught at Northwestern University. In addition, he received a postdoctoral fellowship to study in the Department of Anthropology at Cambridge University, then with the coming of war left to spend several months conducting a field study of the black population of St. Thomas in the Virgin Islands. Early in 1942 he joined Rensis Likert and a staff of social scientists in Washington, D.C., to work providing information to federal agencies on various social and economic problems that had arisen as a result of the war. His title was Assistant Head of the Division of Program Surveys of the Bureau of Agricultural Economics.
Campbell was one of a group of scholars who came out of the Division of Program Surveys dedicated to establishing a new kind of survey research facility in a university setting. Given encouragement by the University of Michigan, Campbell, Likert and others came to Ann Arbor in 1946 to set up the Survey Research Center, one of the units out of which the Institute for Social Research ultimately evolved. He headed the SRC from 1948 to 1970, at which time he succeeded Rensis Likert as ISR director.
Campbell was most closely associated with survey research in three areas: political behavior, racial attitudes, and quality of life studies. He directed a long-time study in political elections that began with the presidential election of 1948. For this and later succeeding studies, Campbell became known as a nationally recognized expert in the field of political surveys.
During the 1960's and at the request of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders, the Survey Research Center undertook a study of race problems in fifteen major cities. Campbell and Howard Schuman were directors of the study which was undertaken early in 1968. Periodically thereafter, Campbell continued to monitor trends in racial attitudes by repeating parts of the study (usually every two years).
Campbell's third major interest was finding ways of conceptualizing and measuring the psychological quality of life. He began work in this area in 1968 with support from the Russell Sage Foundation.
In addition to his responsibilities at ISR, Campbell was Professor of Sociology and Psychology at the University and a lecturer in the Law School. He also served on many University committees.
Campbell was active in many professional organizations and served as a consultant to government agencies. He was an author and editor, and much in demand as a speaker. He died on December 15,1980 at his home in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
The papers of Angus Campbell consist of correspondence, administrative materials, proposals, files relating to various surveys, writings, speeches, and lecture notes. While there are papers going back to 1949, the bulk of the collection dates from the 1960's. The series in the collection are: Biographical Material; Conferences; Correspondence; Institute for Social Research-Survey Research Center; Memberships; University of Michigan Committee Assignments; Off-Campus Assignments; Professional Organizations and Activities; Publications; Speeches; Teaching Files; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Campbell, Angus, 1910-1980; Elections--United States.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; Quality of life.; Race relations.; Social surveys--Research.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Campbell, Angus, 1910-1980; Likert, Rensis, 1903-1981; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  Biographical material has been placed at the beginning of the collection and includes congratulatory letters, awards, bibliographies, biographical sketches, and clippings.
  - Appointment as ISR Director, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Awards
    - American Psychological Association, Distinguished Scientific Contribution Award, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Council for Applied Social Research, Lazarsfeld Award, 1977 (Box 1)
    - International Society of Political Psychology, Harold D. Lasswell Award, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Michigan, University of, Distinguished Achievement Award, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Strathclyde, University of, Glasgow, Honorary Degree, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketches (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
- Conferences
  - International Conference on Comparative Electoral Behavior, Ann Arbor, 1967 (Box 1)
  - International Conference on Comparative Political Sociology, Fin, 1963 (Box 1)
  - UNESCO Round Table on Social Research Policy and Organization, Denmark, 1969 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1950-1980
  The correspondence has been separated into subseries of domestic, foreign, and personal, and then alphabetically.
  - Domestic
    - A-D Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - American Psychological Association (Box 1)
    - American Sociological Association (Box 1)
    - American Statistical Association (Box 1)
    - Bauer, Raymond (Box 1)
    - Cooper, Homer (Box 1)
    - Davies, James (Box 1)
    - Davis, James A. (Box 1)
    - Davis, Robert (Box 1)
    - de Grazio, Alfred (Box 1)
    - E-J Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Garmezy, Norman (Box 1)
    - Hyman, Herbert (Box 1)
    - K-M Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Lansing, John B. and Marjorie (Box 1)
    - Likert, Rensis (Box 1)
    - Mack, Ruth P. (Box 1)
    - Mason, Robert (Box 1)
    - Meyer, Philip (Box 1)
    - Minnesota Poll (Box 1)
    - N-R Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Requests for Information (Box 1)
    - Requests for Publications (Box 1)
    - S-Z Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Schooler, Kermit (Box 1)
    - Smythe, Dallas (Box 1)
    - Stokes, Donald (Box 1)
    - Sussman, Marvin (Box 1)
    - Truman, David (Box 1)
    - Tunstall, Daniel B. (Box 1)
    - Wheatley, Parker (Box 1)
    - Wispe, Lauren (Box 1)
  - Foreign
    - A-K Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Abrams, Mark (Box 1)
    - Brand, Jack (Box 1)
    - Bynner, John (Box 1)
    - Cherns, Albert B. (Box 1)
    - Dupeux, Georges (Box 1)
    - Field, Harry (Box 1)
    - Friis, Henning (Box 1)
    - Hall, John (Box 2)
    - L-Z Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - McKennell, Aubrey C. (Box 2)
    - Moss, Louis (Box 2)
    - Padioleau, Jean (Box 2)
    - Pesonen, Pertti (Box 2)
    - Rapaport, Edmund (Box 2)
    - Rokken, Stein (Box 2)
    - Rose, Richard (Box 2)
    - Sarlvik, Bo (Box 2)
    - Silvey, Robert (Box 2)
    - Valen, Henry (Box 2)
    - Westerstahl, Jorgen (Box 2)
  - Personal, A-Z, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Institute for Social Research-Survey Research Center
  A large part of the collection relates to Campbell's activities at the Institute for Social Research. These papers relate to the administration of the Institute and to surveys conducted by the Survey Research Center. Survey files contain background information, proposals, questionnaires, clippings, correspondence, and reports. Though some of the files are not as complete as others, the most extensive are those relating to election studies, higher education, quality of life, racial attitudes, and social change.
  - Administrative Materials, 1960-1970; 1977 (Box 2)
  - Affirmative Action, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Building Project, 1970; 1974 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Social Psychological Change, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Institutional Review, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Memoranda, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Grant for Institutional Development
    - Application for Support, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Budgets, 1970-1971; 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - General Support Needs, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 2)
  - Program of Research Support for Postdoctoral Scholars at the ISR, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Rackham Grant for Travel Funds, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Seminars
    - Changes in American Life, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Social Indicators, 1970-1972; 1976 (Box 2)
    - Subjective Indicators, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Surveys
    - American Attitudes Toward China
      - Correspondence with Council on Foreign Relations, 1964 (Box 2)
      - General File, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Election Studies
      - Interviews based on Election Studies, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - Presidential Election of, 1964; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Surge and Decline: A Study of Electoral Change, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Fate Control (Box 3)
    - Fraternity Study, 1961 (Box 3)
    - German Embassy Study, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Higher Education
      - Higher Education and the Public, 1960-1963 (Box 3)
      - Public Concepts of the Costs and Utility of Higher Education
        - Action Program, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
        - Correspondence
          - American Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities, 1961-1965 (Box 3)
          - Miscellaneous, 1962-1965 (Box 3)
          - Office of Education, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
        - Proposal, 1962 (Box 3)
        - Reports, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - The Public's Picture of Higher Education in the State of Michigan, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Jackson (MI) Time Use Survey, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Materials relating to Survey Research (Box 3)
    - Quality of Life
      - Correspondence, 1970-1975; 7 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1980; 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Russell Sage Foundation, 1970-1977 (Box 4)
      - Lectures based on Quality of Life Studies (Box 4)
      - Memoranda, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Papers
        - Frank M. Andrews and Stephen B. Withey (Box 4)
        - Angus Campbell and Robert L. Kahn (Box 4)
        - Pauline S. Sears and Ann H. Barbee (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Proposals
        - National Institute of Mental Health, 1977 (Box 4)
        - National Science Foundation
          - 1963 (Box 4)
          - 1971 (Box 4)
          - 1977 (Box 4)
          - 1978-1979 (Box 4)
        - Russell Sage Foundation
          - 1969-1970 (Box 4)
          - 1975 (Box 4)
      - Quality of Life in the Detroit Metropolitan Area, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Surveys in United Kingdom (Mark Abrams and John Hall) (Box 4)
    - Racial Attitudes (Fifteen Cities Study)
      - Background Material, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1967-1979; 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Data File Documentation
        - Black Respondents (Box 5)
        - White Respondents (Box 5)
      - Ecological Bases of Racial Experiences and Attitudes, 1969-1973 (Box 5)
      - Efficacy Tables, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Methodological Reports, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous Materials Relating to Study, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Papers
        - The Effects of Black and White Interviewers on Black Responses in, 1968 (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
        - Racial Trends:, 1964-1974 (Box 5)
        - Stability and Change in Racial Attitudes:, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
      - Study Description (Box 5)
      - White Attitudes Toward Black People, 1968-1971 (Box 5)
    - Social Change
      - National Science Foundation Project
        - Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 5)
        - General File (Box 5)
        - Proposal for a Continuing Study of Social Change, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - Russell Sage Foundation Project
      - Correspondence, 1967-1971; 4 folders (Box 5)
      - General File (Box 5)
    - Television and Politics, 1961-1966 (Box 5)
- Memberships
  - Azazels, 1965-1980 (Box 6)
  - Economic Dinner Group, 1971-1977 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Society of Fellows, 1973-1980; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Quadrangle, 1954-1966 (Box 6)
  - Research Club., 1966-1977 (Box 6)
- University of Michigan Committee Assignments
  - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, 1962-1967; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Budget Priorities Committee, 1972-1978; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Bureau of Industrial Relations Advisory Committee, 1949-1956 (Box 6)
  - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts
    - Committee on the Deanship, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Committee on the Utilization of Faculty Resources, 1956-1958 (Box 6)
    - Executive Committee
      - 1963-1964 (Box 6)
      - 1968-1971 (Box 6)
  - Cook Lectureship Committee, 1966-1978 (Box 6)
  - Detroit Area Study Executive Committee, 1957-1964 (Box 6)
  - Ford Foundation Grants, Special Committee on Research in the Behavioral Sciences
    - 1955-1960, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1961-1963 (Box 7)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1961-1964 (Box 7)
  - Human Resources, 1956-1957 (Box 7)
  - Mental Health Research Institute Advisory Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 7)
  - New Detroit Committee, 1967-1981 (Box 7)
  - Ph.D. Review Committee, 1976 (Box 7)
  - SACUA
    - Intellectual Freedom and Integrity, 1954-1956 (Box 7)
    - Public Relations, 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - University Press Executive Committee, 1962-1976 (Box 7)
- Off-Campus Assignments
  - Bergen, Norway, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Bordeaux, France, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Oslo, Norway, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
- Professional Organizations and Activities
  Professional organizations and activities contain papers relating to Campbell's participation in professional organizations and his work as a consultant. Included are correspondence, minutes, and papers relating to conferences.
  - American Association for Public Opinion Research
    - Committee on Recruitment and Training, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
    - Editorial Board of Public Opinion Quarterly, 1960-1966 (Box 7)
  - American Psychological Association
    - Committee on Academic Freedom and Employment, 1961-1964 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Intraprofessional Relationships, 1950-1973 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Scientific and Professional Responsibility, 1956-1961 (Box 7)
  - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, 1965; 1969 (Box 7)
  - Bureau of Labor Statistics, Consumer Expenditure Survey Advisory Committee, 1960-1962 (Box 7)
  - California, University of-Berkeley, Consultant to Institute for Survey Research, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Council for the Advancement of Science Writing, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Foundation for Research on Human Behavior, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Housing and Urban Development, Research and Development on Urban Problems, 1968 (Box 7)
  - National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, 1970 (Box 7)
  - National Research Council
    - Assembly of Behavioral and Social Sciences, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Building Research Advisory Board, 1970-1973; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Committee on the Sonic Boom
      - Correspondence, 1964-1970 (Box 7)
      - Reports 1965,1977, 1962 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Urban Technology-Committee on Social and Behavioral Urban Research, 1967-1969 (Box 8)
    - Panel on the Significance of Community in the Metropolitan Environment, 1971 (Box 8)
  - Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development, 1971-1975; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Russell Sage Foundation, Advisory Committee on Social Indicators, 1966-1975 (Box 8)
  - Social Science Research Council
    - Committee on Political Behavior, 1952-1965; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Committee on Social Behavior, 1952 (Box 8)
    - Conferences
      - Expectations, Uncertainty and Business Behavior, 1955 (Box 8)
      - Informed Leadership, 1951 (Box 8)
      - Research Into Political Behavior, 1949 (Box 8)
      - Subjective Indicators of Quality of Life, 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1968; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Social Security Administration, Advisory Panel for Social Security Cooperative Research and Demonstration Grant Program, 1961-1963 (Box 8)
  - Space Task Group, 1969 (Box 8)
- Publications
  The Publications series contains background information, correspondence, clippings, reprints, and typescripts. The series has been arranged by title or subject.
  - Dissertation, Stanford University, 1936 (Box 8)
  - A la recherche d'un modele en psychologic electorale comparative (Comparative Research on the Psychology of the Vote), 1966-1967 (Box 8)
  - Administering Research Organizations, 1953 (Box 8)
  - The American Way of Mating, 1975 (Box 8)
  - The Case of the Missing Democrats, 1956 (Box 8)
  - Childless or Child-Free, 1975 (Box 8)
  - Civil Rights and the Vote for President, 1967-1971 (Box 9)
  - Editorial, Letters to the Editor, 1964-1965; 1968 (Box 9)
  - Elections and the Political Order, 1963-1968 (Box 9)
  - Elections (Miscellaneous articles)
    - 1954-1958 (Box 9)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 9)
    - 1964, 1967-1968; 1973; 1980 (Box 9)
    - Undated (Box 9)
  - Irregularities in Survey Data, 1980 (Box 9)
  - Likert, Rensis Biography, 1977-1978 (Box 9)
  - Mass Media (Miscellaneous articles), 1951; 1953; 1963; 1966 (Box 9)
  - The National Election of 1964, 1964-1966 (Box 9)
  - Papers presented at Meetings, 1949-1977 (Box 9)
  - Party Identification in Norway and the United States, 1960-1964 (Box 9)
  - Political Issues and the Vote:, November 1952; 1953 (Box 9)
  - Political Party Identification and Attitudes Toward Foreign Policy, 1951-1952 (Box 9)
  - Politics Through the Life Cycle, 1969-1971 (Box 9)
  - Polling, Open Interviewing, and the Problem of Interpretation, 1946 (Box 9)
  - Prospects for, November, 1962 (Box 9)
  - Quality of Life/Sense of Well-Being (Miscellaneous), 1973; 1976 (Box 9)
  - Race Relations (Miscellaneous) (Box 9)
  - St. Thomas Negroes and Note on the Jewish Community of St. Thomas, 1942-1943 (Box 9)
  - Television and Politics, 1962-1966 (Box 9)
  - Who Are the Non-Voters, 1963-1964 (Box 9)
  - The World of the Young--1957, 1978; 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Reviews by Angus Campbell, 1951-1977; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Reviews of Campbell's books
    - The Perceived Quality of Life, 1974 (Box 9)
    - The Sense of Well-Being in America, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
- Speeches
  The Speech series contains background information, correspondence, clippings, reprints, and typescripts. It has been arranged by name of the sponsoring organization, with title and date also given. The miscellaneous speech folders consist only of notes, outlines, and typescripts of the addresses.
  - American Institute of Certified Public Accountants, Measuring the Quality of Life, 1971 (Box 9)
  - Annual Business Conference of School of Business Administration, Social Accounting in the, 1970s; 1970 (Box 9)
  - California-Orange County Forum and University of California, Santa Barbara (series of lectures), 1972 (Box 9)
  - Carroll College, Social Conflict in Contemporary America, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Center for Continuing Education of Women, Women at Home and at Work, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Conference on Aging, UM, The Politics of Age, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Conference on the Role of the Mass Media in a Democratic Society, University of Texas, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Cornell University, Recent Social Trends to Social Indicators--and Beyond, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Council for the Advancement of Science Writing, The Quality of Life, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Eastern Psychological Association, The Psychological Quality of Life, 1977 (Box 10)
  - International Sociological Association, Social Psychology and Quality of Life, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Midwest Conference of Political Scientists Panel on Ethics, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Minnesota Family Study Center, Quality of Life, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Oklahoma State University Family Study Center, Life-Styles, Free Time and Well-Being, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Oregon State University, The Situation of American Women, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Southern Historical Association, Voters and Elections: Past and Present, 1963 (Box 10)
  - State University of New York at Buffalo, Quality of Life: Are We Making Progress?, 1977 (Box 10)
  - University Press Club, Political Behavior, 1966 (Box 10)
  - University of Puget Sound, Who Voted and Why: An Analysis of the Candidate Support, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Vermont Conference on the Primary Prevention of Psychopathology, Indicators of Perceived Well-Being, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Wisconsin State University, Can the Republicans Win in, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 10)
- Teaching Files
  - Case Studies in Survey Research (Psych 684-Soc 614) 1965,1967, 1962-1963; 1969 (Box 10)
  - Quantitative Analysis of Legal Problems, 1963-1964; 1966 (Box 10)
  - Socio-Legal Seminar, 1968-1980 (Box 10)
- Photographs
  - Portraits and photos of ISR Building, 1 folders (Box 10)